[Music]
all right
hello and welcome everyone
this is actin flab live stream number
35.1
it's january 5th 2022.
welcome to the active inference lab we
are a participatory online lab that is
communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference you can find us
at the links here on this slide
this is a recorded and an archived live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so that we can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome here
and we'll be following good video
etiquette for live streams plus playing
with our new affordance thanks to our
jitsi repair person
and uh that'll be
fun go to activeinference.org if you
want to learn more about how to
participate or get involved if you're
listening to this live stream
live or in replay allocating your regime
of attention this way then maybe you'd
like to get involved a little bit more
actively with projects including
planning the live stream
so today we are in active stream 35.1 we
are discussing the paper that dean and
blue and i did 35.0 on yesterday and
that paper is a tale of two
architectures
free energy it's models and modularity
by majeed benny in december 2021
and we're gonna be
talking modifying slides asking
questions going into some things that we
brought up in the dot zero
connecting a few dots and also preparing
for hopefully majeed to join in the dot
two video
we're going to be discussing this again
next week at the same time
so
let's begin with some introduction and
warm-up we will
each go around and just say hello and
introduce ourselves
as well as maybe just add something that
we're curious about what got us really
excited to discuss this paper and what
are we looking forward to reducing our
uncertainty about in the coming
days and weeks
so i'll start i'm daniel i'm a
researcher in california
and i think i'm excited to talk about
the information encapsulation and what
that means as well as to go into that
parable of alice and bob and see who
here wants to
relay that story to us and
shine some light on narrative based
understandings of free energy principle
and i'll pass it to stephen
thank you yeah i'm stephen i'm here in
toronto
i'm really interested in um
this ability to step back and look at
some of the underlying
uh processes of actually modelling that
this talks about
and the philosophies of that in quite a
practical way so i uh
i'm i'm excited by that potential from
this paper so and also what the group
here is making of that because i think
it's a it's challenging us to start to
think about some foundational stuff in
our work so
um i'm going to pass this over to
dave we're going to just skip dave for
some audio
oh
dean is dean amount yep
uh my i'm dean i'm in calgary
uh for me it's always trying to be able
to hold up two things at once and so for
those two things in this paper or the
moment of instantiation or the sort of
the model slice aspect of
what we're looking at and then
also to instantiate her to modulate and
so
those two things together what does that
imply and that's what i want to talk
about a little bit today with bob and
ellis and i'll
pass it to blue
hi i'm blue i'm a research consultant in
new mexico
and something i'm excited to talk about
today is or maybe next week um is the
idea of modularity in the free energy
principle and how that might work in the
absence of a brain where the fep still
applies to brainless systems and how how
that might be also modular or not
okay
so there's so many
places to jump in but thankfully we have
some questions in the live chat which
we'll begin with and then as per usual
we will
modify our slides
and just keep on adding more slides
adding more questions so if you're
watching live thanks again for all these
great questions and i'll
uh first bring them into this slide so
joseph clark asks
this is a little bit of a general
question and then we'll move to a
question that's a bit more specific to
the paper so the general question is
there a space space
on either the discord or live streams to
discuss active inference in reference to
more traditional philosophical
psychological linguistic or social
science questions
what would anyone say on that
well i suppose that
that that we
do have some of those conversations as
part of the active inference lab um
some of the social science questions um
it can get in the weeds um with too many
different
assumptions in the background which they
themselves could be contentious so
i think it's helpful
to do some of the type of work that
we're doing now to sort of think about
what does it actually mean to model
something what are the sort of
assumptions
that are even going on
before we start to dive into
broad
sort of popular
theoretical frameworks because
are we going to come at this from
the position of um
[Music]
a very low dimensional modeling approach
which is shed light onto things like
autism things like schizophrenia things
like
types of behavior
or are we going to come at this more
from a
structured principled approach
where we have an ecological niche
relating to an agent and a generative
model
some of those things i think are more
helpful to
start to pass
so that we know
how we're locating the discussion but
i'm not sure if others agree with that
because it's very easy to get caught up
in a discussion which is essentially
located
in
say the social sciences
and trying to work from there with all
the implicit assumptions and get back to
active influence
and it can get quite heady and kind of
confusing
it's maybe better working the other way
addressing something
from okay how do we take a type of
modeling approach used around fep active
inference in relation to something
what's useful from that but that's
that's my uh
that's my feeling and uh i also believe
it's nice to do stuff where you're doing
interactive dialogue and working with
documents in real time as much as it is
through
a text chat because i think that also
can start to get it can't quite handle
the level of complexity at play
thanks steven blue
so i would push back on joseph um for a
specific example of a question that
might fall into this category um and
also um
is there a particular paper that that
might be related to active inference in
this field uh because i do feel like we
do discuss a lot of philosophical
and social science questions i'm not
sure i guess there's some linguistics
also i can't remember like a stream it's
just not like like linking in my brain
but um i mean we just did um thinking
like a state which is very social
science based i think and um so yeah i
would just love to see what particular
questions you would like to see
addressed and if you can find a paper
and recommend it uh that we discuss on
the live stream more than happy to
accommodate that
um yeah yep the linguistics
guest stream was eliot murphy so i'll
respond in terms of affordances i think
there are probably more so create your
own affordance modify the acting flab as
your niche as you see fit but
there's always the informal discord
affordance just post in general and say
hey everyone i'm gonna be
curious about these ideas i don't even
know
what to know but i'm gonna be curious
about these different things these
topics these three questions and uh in
two hours i'll be doing it or in two
weeks at this time so you can always
just say when you're gonna be in the
voice chat on discord and maybe some
people will drop in or you can invite
some friends specifically and then a
little bit more formal of an affordance
is we can host a guest stream or a panel
so that would be done through the
dot-coms organizational unit and we
would work to plan the timing and then
also set up the discussion so it's not
just like we show up and it's like okay
well who is going to prepare like we can
just
to whatever extent is required
get a jamboard ready get some slides
ready some questions that will spark the
conversation and that can also invite
people outside of the active community
so it can be whatever you like so by
asking the question you've signaled that
you understand that such an affordance
could be important and so
looking forward to seeing how you follow
through
so let's go to
joseph's second question which brings us
i think a little bit closer towards the
paper
it will uh
zoom in towards it so how do you stop
overfitting on one layer of the model
for example leg movements to avoid
compromising the larger goal that an
agent or person wants to do like kicking
a football
i feel this question may also help put
some of the debates around modularity
versus hierarchical information
segregation in an analogous context
so it's a
great
question we talked a lot about
hierarchical modeling
and about that lateral modularity kind
of the collective behavior element
and then the nested
modularity
which is the multi-scale systems
perspective
and in active inference as we explored
with the mental action paper and deep
active inference
we sometimes have these nested models
that are expanding over multiple time
scales
so that the action at one time step
isn't just greedily pursuing the overall
preference
but rather the preference can be
realized or uncertainty about realizing
the preference can be achieved through
policy selection over a given time
horizon even when the micro movements
might not be
um
intuitive so sort of taking one step
back so that you can
go a better path
what would anybody
add to that or we can start to diagram
some pieces out here
i would just say don't don't
drop one or the other don't drop the
idea of the moment of instantiation or
that model slice
and don't drop the ins to instantiate or
to modulate
make sure that like i i've used the
expression when it does zoom in zoom out
when you're zooming out you're actually
trying to incorporate longer time frames
versus a moment in time and and that's
how i would
that's how i would mitigate some you
keep i don't know that you can wipe out
the overfitting problem there's always
potential for that
but you can mitigate it somewhat by
making sure that you
keep the two
ideas
up at the same time without one blending
into the other or total focus on one or
the other
all right i threw up a image from
uh
paper 25
which was the mental action paper of
sandvik smith
and
um this is kind of
one way to address it
so let's just say that the overall goal
were to kick the football it's a good
example you know it works for whichever
side of the pond you're on with kicking
the football
the overall preference would be for for
example the sensory observation of
seeing the football far away
or of observing the
foot making contact with the football
at
high velocity
and the foot is starting in a neutral
position
so just sort of like standing
and the greedy gradient descender
would just go from the neutral position
to just kick forward
but maybe it's possible there's like a
three-step movement for example in the
first time step you pull the leg back
and then you move it forward two times
so over three clicks of time
in the model
that is going to be
the outcome that ultimately best
realizes your preferences of making
contact with your foot on the ball at
the maximum possible velocity
and so
the policy selection is happening at the
motor level so the policy here is a
parameter that's describing like
the angle of the hip
that is the um
state that's being inferred so we won't
go too deep into the skilled performance
angle or the
interactionism angle but 23 check it out
um and
two policies
can be
compared or a whole family of policies
can be compared with one another one
policy is just move the like forward the
other policy is move leg backwards then
forward twice another policy would be
like move it backwards then forwards and
backwards and forwards never kick the
ball
then over a given time horizon like the
time that the organism has to make this
kick
different expectations can be calculated
for different policy
sequences
and again if it turns out that moving
the leg back one step and then forward
two steps makes contact with the ball at
higher velocity then
at the
level of deep policy selection that
three-step sequence will be selected
over
the
just move the leg forward sequence or
the back and forth
not kicking sequence
so that's a mechanical
version
and
it's also the kind of model structure
that applies to not just motor actions
but mental action
so i hope that gets a little bit towards
it and also starts us towards this
discussion of modularity because
where is the modularity in what we just
described so steven and then anyone else
who raises their hands or throws out a
string of emojis
yeah this is a very useful
example um
um
because you see how it's about
phenomenology
um and it's interesting because
traditionally philosophical
psychological perspectival type
uh approaches
averaging out over social
approaches
um
aren't phenomenological
and phenomenological ties in more
with our best guess approach of how an
agent is experiencing things so in what
you just mentioned here i think this is
quite good for the kick and the
footballers i'm trying to work out how
to kick the football what am i trying to
do as i said in policy selection i'm
trying to work out the best way to do it
and i may be unaware of what i'm paying
attention to
in trying to help do that there might be
some subconscious processes which are
helping to calibrate it however once
i've actually mastered
that
performance what i'm paying attention to
may not be how to do it i might be in
the flow and now my what am i paying
attention to is how do i look up and
just kick the ball
towards another player so i think that
i'm wondering what people's thoughts are
there in terms of how that changes
things to now be in an agent-based mode
good
question i think it also relates to the
event-based cognition for example martin
butz and what he talked about
um
the micro level is indeed the policy of
each muscle and joint
being selected to
write something
however
there's a modularity
that arises
from cognitive chunking
of complex motor actions for example
into
broader more handleable
units so like writing a letter
is like a unit of motor actions it's
actually a
really complex sequence of motor actions
and then writing a word is a given event
that subsumes
or entails or requires or
is supervening upon
lower level policy selections like which
way to move a muscle of a thumb
however it's
the um increasingly chunked
and modular perhaps even semantic levels
that
appear to arise more to our
phenomenology which is why we
for example reach for something and a
whole host of processes
play out without us needing to
micromanage the
motor actions
yes uh dean
oh uh
i was just
kind of
i think what to steven's point i think
what we are asking here is
does the mind
or can the mind go in two directions
namely do we start with a frame or an
architectural scaffold or a model
or
does the process
of of what we're watching i.e kicking a
ball
spectralize the relativity i.e does it
confirm what the edges are
so those are those are different
completely opposite views of things over
over a time scale so then
i guess what we have to ask ourselves is
does the representation
act as the takeoff point meaning do we
start with the model do we start with
that scientific view or
and or does the representation
evolve as the results sort of more the
creative view i think we're capable of
doing both
in fact there's lots of evidence that we
do do both so i would come back to
do we modulate yes is that a process yes
do we can we take slices of a modulation
exercise
and see them as representational
and and modeling yes
so that's all i would point to i don't
know when the transition is stephen when
it's kicking a ball
banksteen stephen and then anyone else
yeah with this transition
this may be part of what changes and i
suppose this is one of the interesting
things is it depends on the nature of
the situation um
but everything at some level which is
interesting
is is hidden in active inference and
we're trying to get some purchase on
that which is interesting as opposed to
it being out there as knowledge
and with and we and we somehow know it
it's like okay what am i perceiving
will always be more hidden states than i
can ever really know
what am i trying to do there with more
hidden states what am i paying attention
to
um and i think what's quite
interesting is what is at the
the the realm of
being available to us in our
consciousness okay so the sort of thing
that daniel was talking about the sort
of process the sense-making process
which is present when it's not
immediately obvious how to kick a ball
because messi doesn't do that messi
knows he just
he feels it right
but the there's a there's something
really interesting about the scale and i
think
my feeling is if we have a meso middle
scale there's things which
come out of our awareness or are harder
to purchase or get a grip on as they
become faster
and
as they become
low slower
so you know what am i paying attention
to there may be something that's
my unconscious is sort of aware of that
phenomenological feeling about how the
events is going and how my stomach is
feeling waiting for the next meal which
is sort of
too slow for me to really notice
and there's other things like we're
saying we should just
biologically at speeds faster than the
rates at which conscious awareness
operates
and we've sort of got
both of these and that moves a little
bit depending on how i take my attention
in the world
thanks steven
yes so
we have a few different
axes or continuum here
there's the phenomenological or what is
experienced and then there's sort of the
third person
impersonal where it's more just about
what's happening in the model and we
don't even associate it with
a conscious experience
in this mental action paper
it threads the line because it is
talking about computational
phenomenology however this is the
structure of deep active inference
policy selection models which don't need
to require any kind of phenomenological
experience
so
blue and then we will continue to the
next slide
so just in thinking about
agent systems and information
encapsulation
it seems like to be part of the same
system there must be partial information
encapsulation like you can't play a
basketball game with a bunch of other
people without sharing
information such as the position of the
ball right like so there's you know and
the rules of the game etc so the
partial information encapsulation i mean
how to what degree like what percentage
is information encapsulated between
individuals between modules of an
individual tissues of an individual and
so forth i really wonder about that i
mean even like you think about the
butterfly effects like we're all sharing
i mean globally information such as
climate change or or this type of thing
so there's there's information at a
global level that affects every single
one of us because we're all part of the
same global system and so
there's gotta be some kind of partial
encapsulation i think
uh um
just to be connected in a system
great stephen
i think that's a good point blue blue
makes there because
there's only certain things available at
certain temporal scales
to make some of these
um
the the the temporal depth of being
aware of the ball
in a in a practical sense
is a certain there's a certain at some
point it just becomes noise it's too
fast to sequence it there's no point
getting
um
outside of actually processing sensory
information itself at these faster
levels and as happens with all the
uncertainty
and error prediction that goes up the
chain there's a certain
goldilocks zone right for knowing
um how the ball is going in the game and
if i'm standing i'm watching the game
there's a sort of a golden lock speed
which is probably relatively slow just
like in a soccer game if i'm sort of
running down the wing and uh not getting
the ball a lot and uh but when the ball
is actually kicked to me i've got a
player coming in to tackle me i've got
another player running and i've got to
do something with it now bang i've got a
window that's got to happen in their
shortest period of time you know the
the the regime of attention and the
action policy selection
is is is in this in the terms of like um
half a second maybe milliseconds of
which some then are not even available
in our conscious awareness unlike maybe
the tracking of the game which might be
of a window of 5 10 15 seconds maybe
longer i think that in itself would that
not itself create some sort of
modularity
great
question so
we explored several different
senses of modularity in the dot zero so
there is the physical connectedness like
the anatomical connectivity
anatomical modularity and then we talked
about the effective and functional which
are two statistically different they're
not interchangeable but they're two
different ways to talk about modularity
um
so now we're exploring how these notions
of modularity line up with potentially
the
nesting of multi-scale systems through
space and time
so i'm pulling up one of the figures
from ramstead at all 2018 answering
schrodinger's question
if i can just resize it properly and so
here on the
x-axis is time and on the y-axis is
spatial scale
and what this graph is
laying out loosely and it's been
described in other papers and
discussions since
is that things are kind of existing
on the
um
line
where we're seeing that smaller things
are happening faster
and larger things are happening slower
things that happen over continents
are happening over longer time scales
than things that can happen at a sub
cellular scale
so there is kind of this natural
relationship between spatial and the
temporal scale of processes
and how does that relate to
the
modularity that blue was describing
if there's complete encapsulation of a
given module
if such a thing could even exist in
reality is one question
now if something could exist in our
model
of course it's true we can develop a
model that has that connectivity amongst
variables doesn't mean it's the best
model or it's the one that is the
perfect
um territory description itself but it's
not it's a map
and then if we had no integration
that's kind of like saying that it's
just encapsulated at the next scale up
um or i'm sorry no encapsulation
within a level is kind of like saying
it's just perfectly encapsulated at the
next level
so in a way the partial information
encapsulation
is the gray zone that everything is
going to be existing within
steven and then anyone else
yeah i mean and actually because they
have they've sort of gone back on this
page on this particular diagram to some
extent after feedback from casper has um
i think this is
really where there is a um
because this continuum this idea of a
continuum going out
is what i think active inference um
sort of
changes how we see that and it's hard
because when we try and map things like
what
maxwell was doing here he was taking
stuff from the social sciences and the
different
approaches that are mainstream and this
is how it pans out
but if this is often because this is
what we
think of something from the outside we
see from the outside groove behavioral
patterns we see an organism we
categorize it we make models of it and
they sort of stack up in this way over
time and
in time and temporal and physical scales
however
from the perspective of the dynamics
are we having a different goldilocks
zone
within smaller and faster temporal
dynamics
in terms of what's actually happening
and when that means something's out in
the niche
we may see stuff dropping out from that
but there's no reason for instance where
niche construction
is not being under
girdled by rapid decision making
at real time
just like the soccer players are all
making choices on the pitch
around where they run it changes the way
the grass is going to get worn down
okay
so
this is interesting actually now looking
at well so what is the replacement to
this diagram
has there been one
that doesn't have this kind of
micro macro and actually is able to have
an action orientated miso that can
meet the requirements of
um
what we're talking about pluralistic
ontologies and ontological pluralism
well where is that
where is that being described and i
think that's a missing link at the
moment
right
i think that this takes us to a uh
good return on the
markov blanket scale free or scale
friendly
debate
because um just like you said stephen
somebody talking about a cellular scale
and the kinds of perception cognition
action happening at a cellular or an
organismal scale
they're not saying that niche
construction
um
doesn't exist ecological scale niche
construction because we could also think
about tissue level niche construction
um
rather that the regime of attention of
the scientific modeler is being directed
towards a given kind of modeling
and so that's sort of
how we take something that is
a unifying
theory like free energy principle
or a scale free or a
[Music]
scale
a priori
model whether it's markov blankets or
linear regression
but in any application to a given system
there are going to be time scales of
analysis that just do and don't make
sense
and
um
that's
where we operationalize the
markov like it or as benny wrote
although markov blankets are in
principle scale free
meaning there are no inherent
constraints on their size and scope
their application or imputation to
various target systems will impose a
definite scale on markov blankets dean
yeah and i think again that's why i want
to talk a little bit about the
instantiation moment
sort of
piggybacking on yours and steven's
comment when we apply a markov blanket
we can ask the question
from an encapsulation perspective did
you see what i saw
it's a question
we're both behind a blanket we're both
wondering
if there's some agreement
that we've gained some sort of a
contextual alignment
i could also say to you
did you see that
which is it
it may sound like almost the same
question but it's not the same question
it's not even it's they're radically
different questions because one says
are we in agreement on what's being
encapsulated
meaning are we are we forming a a
co-contextualization or the other one
says
uh i'm not sure
right so i'm not sure what you're seeing
so to this question of scale
it's it's it free energy is moving us i
think to that place of
of coexisting context
but i think the critical thing is
we've talked about this so many times
don't don't confuse the
to something or other the map with the
field or whatever i just get i get lost
in it all but but the bottom line is
can we do two things at once i know we
can our brains can
realize that applying a partition
versus or with
in in conjunction with what is that
slice of time
as a relativity question and then when
does that relativity question appear at
the beginning is that our takeoff point
or is that our conclusion
that's all that this paper to me does is
it says at what moment do we employ
categorization
interesting dean thank you dave and then
anyone else
um yeah you know to dean's uh comment
uh when i asked did you see what i saw
the
proximal
pull
of your attention is being invited to be
projected into me
so you're seeing it
through me
you might compare that to what some
crazy russians were doing a hundred
years ago
they were uh
trying to get the notion across that
very few people are conscious more than
a few times a year
and they said well look i can explain
away your impression that you're
conscious a whole lot
here's what i can say i can say hey are
you conscious
the very fact that i asked you are you
conscious causes you to be conscious
it shocks you into consciousness and you
wake up and you say well yes i am of
course you are because
and this takes in the idea of
what is
the adjacent possible
what is available in that ecosystem for
awareness that we're talking about so
just like you said there if someone says
did you see that
that can take someone into a sense of
like i'm trying to work out
often
particularly if there's a power
difference between people
um
what that other person's now
wanting me to see
and i've seen this a lot actually when
we're doing work in south africa with
communities one of the first things is
to let people
and you ask them a question to get them
to a point where
they're actually
telling you what they think
not what they think you
are thinking about what they should be
saying
okay so where is
that attention just like say it where is
it in terms of being conscious as an
awareness
and how much of this scale is well
what's available
and what's going to be an impact
in terms of the adjacency so a cell
has some awareness potentially maybe
even some adaptive inference at the kind
of
at the actual organ level potentially
and maybe further
it will have an impact maybe in terms of
the way cells divide on the nature of
speciation
yes there's it's it's but it hasn't
necessarily got
any trajectory to adaptively
um couple it it's not in its adjacent
possibles and i think that is quite
useful
in terms of it starts to open up in
terms of the information either
temporally how much is something
separated by time
spatially how much it by space but i
suppose also by statistical
contingencies
and the ability to adapt and interact
those types of things well what is
either within or adjacent and what
becomes outside of that
i think that starts to
give some of these
these scaly modularity questions just
maybe an applied
direction to come out
thank you stephen blue
there is a huge fundamental difference
between asking someone what do you see
and do you see that even if you don't um
give them that you're still looking in a
direction of that
right so the what do you see like lets
someone
look at their surroundings take stock in
what they see and give their independent
observations versus just even like do
you see that and like you look over in a
direction at least like you're directing
someone's intent attention
with your question so asking an open
question versus a directed question can
give very different answers
and i wonder what
the impact of that would be on
modularity like
or even just an information sharing like
there's more shared information in do
you see that or do you see what i see
that's like
like an intention to share your
generative model at that point
versus what do you see is actually
trying to take stock in someone else's
model it's just an interesting thought
yeah
these all
point
using the example of communication and
visual perception to
where we have partial information
encapsulation
if the two entities were totally
encapsulated they couldn't communicate
if there was no encapsulation such a
question wouldn't be required to be
asked but there's a
specific type of edge
in this
network we could almost think of these
like two modules as like maybe the two
generative models of the individuals and
there's this connection
when some of the modules are
connected
and it is a
nice how we're kind of exploring these
subtly different questions i think did
you see that
is
that is corresponding to an external
state like an observation did you see
that that
red blur in the sky
i don't know what it was could have been
a comment but did you see that versus
what i saw um
well we know that you see with your mind
generative model of vision and whatnot
and so especially when we're
outside of the signal processing
paradigm of vision
did you see what i saw is like quite
literally asking is your internal hidden
state
related to mine are we seeing the same
thing
that doesn't mean are the photons
hitting both of our retina it means do
we have a shared generative model of
visual objects
so
dean
and then dave
just one last thing that's a great
summary first of all
secondly um
when we're talking about
what is the nature of the partition
we're we're i think as a group we're
still
trying to define what we
hope is
is is not completely definable yet
do you want to understand with that
partial encapsulation
not saying it's undefined i'm not saying
it's zero although
down the road i might say we're passing
through zero because that's what i i'm
kind of
moving towards but i think
when we partition
that partition
is not
static
and it's not and the
the definition of it is to leave it
somewhat
undefined
that's
i like your explanation better daniel
but
that's what i think we're trying to move
towards here
eventually great dave do you want to
add something there
okay
so um
uh
blue
or if not blue then stephen
i went already i'm good
i suppose just pushing a question back
we talk about this encapsulation
modularity
and where we
put that by putting the blanket
somewhere
seems to be
kind of implied by that
so
that kind of is
done through
a way of speculating on where the
observations
are generating some
sensory states
and where we are in terms of the action
dynamics at play how much is this
dropping out of
the literal availability
at a certain scale
and then we make the blanket around it
and how much of it comes from structure
in the blanket
in terms of how we implement this i
think
i think that changes what modularity may
or may not mean
um
because i think that
how those
separations of modularity are done
you know is it is it a case of how
sort of parallel processes are happening
and are being integrated and they're
modularly almost independent maybe
certain senses are independent and how
much is it that they're independent
um
because they're separated at an
integrated level
by temporal physical space
great
questions
are these partitionings
are
a priori model
or do we merely specify what we're going
to measure and then the blankets if
we're using the technical definition of
a markov blanket like the set of
variables
upon which two other sets of variables
called internal and external states
become conditionally independent
in that case you don't need to specify
which nodes are blanket states you just
make the measurements
and then
relative to a target set of states some
other set become
a blanket with respect to a third
external
type of states
so dean
and then blue
okay i'll be super quick
this idea that our minds are able to
categorize
it's a world of segregations like in
backslashes when we're looking at
symbolically or integrations i.e hyphens
these are symbolic knots to the market
up markov blanketing
so the instantiating
or partitioning of an applica
partitioning
and applying i'm sorry
so my example here might be a little
strange but
be generous
when yellow becomes orange in an fmri
or a rainbow
which begs the question is a rainbow a
piece of encapsulated information
okay
is that representation transitive or
intransitive
okay so i.e the claim that the most
important color in the rainbow is yellow
on one end
on the other is at the end of all
rainbows must exist prisms made up of
unicorns sea serpents and flying monkeys
or maybe free
and energy and dynamic or principle
see where i'm going with this our minds
are able to do
both ends of that continuum at once
and that's what i think that where the
architecture and the process
both come into play
if we can look at this from us from a
support more of a did you see what i saw
perspective and most people won't say
they're comparing flying monkeys to
free energy
dynamics but people can
and maybe i think maybe that's what
affordance our minds are trying to set
up here it certainly is with how we
encapsulate the information how we as
the observer choose to do that and then
try to gain some consensus around that
thank you for your patience
late nights in the dean household
um blue and then stephen
tickles me just tickles me
um so i have to just comment on dean's
comment really quickly and then i want
to go back to what stephen said so
um when yellow becomes orange in an fmri
now i don't really
know a lot about how fmri works but i
don't think that there's actually any
color spectra applied like yellow is
570 to 590 nanometers in the
electromagnetic spectrum but i don't
think that fmri actually turns out
yellow i think it actually turns out
something between 0 and
256. so like in terms of light intensity
and we just fakely apply yellow to that
right that's correct right yeah so so
it's an arbitrary distinction when
yellow becomes orange or rainbow
like this is just something we made up
um
um just you know
to to share our generative model like to
share information about the picture that
we're seeing on the screen um but but
going back to what stephen said and then
this is going to hit on a point that
dean is going to love also
you know
because we apply
the markov blanket to the system that
we're interested in studying like to the
organism the individual the heart the
liver the cell to to define what makes
the internal and external states
conditionally independent we apply the
blanket
therefore we create the module is that
the same or is that not the same
i vote saying are we engaged in module
projection or module discovery and
not even or or what other
ways do modules apply so stephen with a
raised hand and then anyone else
so there are two two interesting points
um just been made there by blue and
in that moment and dean
what when we say doing both at once
i think there's also times i would argue
though
that we're able to do both and some of
these processes can be
possibly be run in parallel however the
regimes of attention at certain scales
we can't do
[Music]
together
in the same way we almost have to go
from one to the other unless there's an
adjacency between the two types of
regimes i would say
to enable that to happen so if i'm
thinking about
something for instance that's quite
somatic
and then i'm thinking about something
which is quite um abstract
over time i might be able to train
myself for that abstract to have a
marker in the somatic that i can then
integrate with but i'm still integrating
two semantics together in the somatic
regime or i might have a model of the
somatic
in the kind of
ocular visual
modeling mode and i can imagine the two
but
in the same moment i can't hold both
with the same type of embodiment
so that's that's one of the things that
i think is quite important
to wonder and then also once we then get
into these is that
um
ability to configure is that
the markov blanket and this sort of
takes us into sense finding sense making
type of work is the sense finding that
okay how am i even sensing what to do in
this moment when we we have that
um and then i start to sense and then
i'm sense making how to do it and then
i'm into skillful practice and maybe i
can just do it
so some things are more or less
um in and out of is that sense finding
sort of a line in the blanket by
basically aligning what the sensory in
action kind of states that are relevant
are going to be done and then are we
maybe have that set and now we're in a
kind of more
um generative sense making maybe even
just skillful flow okay okay i've got my
general blanket in place i'm in a
skillful flow now right um
and
that sometimes takes time you know
um and it's also maybe you know we can
only switch attention to something
that's in a different regime with a
certain speed you know
um so anyway at both those points really
struck me
the speed of attention it's really
interesting
and
pristine and others have related that to
the
rapid oscillations like the gamma cycles
in the brain
which you know they don't happen a
hundred thousand times per second but
they do happen more than once a second
they there's a certain number of times
and it's interesting how that lines up
with our
uh perceptual
capacity like when something is like
alternating and rotating and then it
goes from sort of black and white to
gray
there's
a moment where the perceptual speed is
just not able to
um
see that anymore as two contrasting
states but it's one blurred state and it
doesn't have to do with the photons
hitting the retina being blurred it has
to do with the generative model of
vision
dean
stephen i completely agree with you and
i i
reference back to sort of wicked
wittgenstein's illusion of the duck
rabbit
and how do we put a markov blanket
between those two representations you
can't see the rabbit when you see the
duck and vice versa
and then that leads me to this the
parable of bob and alice so i just
wanted to put that in there i think
that's a great time let's um
move bob and alice up let's put bob and
alice on their own page with a with a
duck
i don't want to even buy us which one it
is with this um
representation so
would you like to maybe set up the bob
and alice or we can look up the um full
text go with the text because it's
really clear yeah awesome all right so
here we go
okay
all right
we're going to assume there are two
neighbors bob and alice so a and b kind
of a classic quantum parable
every night when bob is beginning to
brush his teeth alice begins to read
a section of a tale of two cities at the
adjunct flat
state b contains bob beginning to brush
his teeth in his flat and state a
contains alice beginning to read
the book at hers
let us assume there is no causal
relationship between the states a and b
given the two states are segregated
there may or may not be a common cause
that pre-establishes a harmony between a
and b
say
when what happens in a and b are both
bedtime activities coordinated because
of various cultural and geographic
habits
however the assumption of common cause
does not need to affect the present
discussion because what is important for
us is that information processing is in
a is inaccessible to information
processing and b and vice versa
this is in harmony with satisfying the
assumption of encapsulation and the
assumption of modularity to some
interesting extent
so dean maybe unpack or explain what you
think is interesting and i'll start to
get some
uh nodes and edges on this slide okay so
i don't know which which
the duck or the rabbit which is bob or
which is alice but to the observer
there's information encapsulated in that
which can be broken down
into a or b
then the question becomes one of so how
do we modulate
how does the switch between those two
different representations held in one
one block of pixels
work
how do we partition
when that
potential for one other or the other
exists did did you see what i saw
i guess we're coming back to that
question
okay
steven and then i'll be
developing these nodes a little bit
yeah and what we see
um
well i'm going to add one thing here is
sort of related i think is if you look
at that rabbit and that duck okay
well
the rabbit is forward looking
and decisive and the back is backward
looking at the past
because
the grip the visual grammar that we use
in the west is mostly that the left of a
vertical
flat image or flat piece of
paper
is the left is the past the right is the
future
so even that flipping
the nature of
that
rabbit is
caught within a cultural frame
okay which would be different if the
duck was facing the other way and the
rabbit was looking backwards
so
um
i suppose there's something interesting
there yeah
yeah now now the the rabbit's like
looking back in the past right
um
so there's there's something interesting
there about um
uh
other kind of uh the contextuality i
suppose of how things are so i just
thought i'd add that in but
yes as the symposium with fristen
discussed a lot illusions reveal our
priors so if you're trained in ballerina
dance and it's only a clockwise rotation
when you see the rotating ballerina
you're going to see that that's going to
be
having overwhelming posterior likelihood
given the ambiguous visual stimuli or if
cubes are always facing down into the
left you're going to perceive that when
you see an ambiguous cubic stimulus
and so it does matter um
these deep priors on how we perceive
even visual stimuli blue
so
there's an important component i think
that's missing from the bobbin alice
paradigm and the author alludes to it in
describing shared cultural norms bedtime
etc
but there's bob and there's alice and
then there's
the niche the environment essentially
that they both reside in the environment
and in the environment it's nine o'clock
and so something interesting that it
reminds me of is um that i was reading
that intransitivity paper i was just
looking for it daniel maybe you have it
in a slide and can reference it here but
they talked about intransitivity in
various contexts and we gave the example
of rock paper scissors but um
they also mentioned intransitivity in
the laptop
population model with the fox and the
rabbit right so normally like you don't
think about that as being an
intransitive um relationship it's like
the foxes go up and the rabbits go down
and the rabbits go up and the fox you
know it's like this cyclical thing
between the fox and the rabbit but they
mentioned the importance of the
environment and how like it's just
normally considered that environmental
resources are constant but that's not
normally the case and so eventually like
if the rabbits eat all the grass the
population of rabbits will go down
unrelated to the population of foxes and
and so it's um i think important to
consider in bob and alice um in this
relationship like what is the role of
the niche environment and then does does
like this third hidden state like okay
we see bob and we see alice and they
don't know anything about each other so
information is encapsulated like bob
doesn't know anything about alice alice
doesn't know anything about bob but they
both live in the same place and that's
what i was saying earlier about the
butterfly effect and climate change like
the environment plays a role in the
distribution of information between bob
and alice
great um
so we can look at two
different stories and i think this
totally gets to the um difference
between realism and instrumentalism as
well
so what are the difference between these
two
these two uh well first off it's funny
that the book being read is um
a tale of two
cities
because
that's like the tale of two den cities
like we read
and it's also invoked in the title of
this paper
so there's going to be
two stories of red lines these are two
narratives that can be told
scientifically by modelers
okay so no one's disagreeing about the
niche no one's saying well they're
they're actually they're in a you know
one's on the moon and one's on earth so
we're talking about the same niche
now let's imagine that bob and alice
were two brain regions b and a so we
observe brushing
and reading
to be co-activated they're co-expressed
behaviors
and so
what does this edge reflect
we have an answer there
it's the functional connectivity
functional connectivity first to 94.
functional connectivity is a temporal
correlation between spatially remote
events
so
that is functional connectivity the
alternative is to
refer to effective connectivity which is
the influence of one neuronal system
over another
let's go back to bob and else so
this is a functional connectivity edge
if there was an effective connectivity
edge
it
would have none
because although they happen at a
temporally correlated time let's just
say they each did it 90 of the time so
overall like 81 percent of the time
they're both doing it
and so there's a really high temporal
correlation however
the 10 percent of the time when one is
not doing it it doesn't have an effect
on the other
so they're conditionally independent so
actually the effective connectivity
wouldn't have an edge if it were
calculated appropriately
so functional connectivity we see an
edge effective connectivity we don't see
an edge and then there's the third
uh story then dean
which is a causal
mechanistic story
which is the niche
broadly being the time zone and the
human circadian rhythms and all these
other features
the niche is influencing bob and alice
independently it's like a confounding
variable
and then
that is what causes bob to brush and
alice to read
and so yes we do get this temporal
correlation
arising from a
latent cause and causing variable
and so
how does that relate to neuroimaging
studies when people find that there's
functional or even effective
connectivity amongst brain regions
and then cast that as a mechanistic
story
about what is actually happening
dean and then stephen
isn't the effective i'm asking because i
don't know is the effect of connectivity
here it on a z
plane meaning
from the observer's standpoint
the effect is
this x y relationship
um
so
because that's time right the changes
through is through that from my eyeballs
through that screen into that slide
and then beyond on the other side of
that is that not the effect of connected
connectivity
i know we can't show it here because we
have to work on on
on 2d rectangles but isn't that it
um
correct you could think about for any
given edge
like between brushing and reading
there's gonna be some function fc score
between zero and one
and then there's some effective
connectivity score between zero and one
yeah and so you could have cases where
that edge is like a zero comma zero
it doesn't have effective nor functional
connectivity in a given experimental
measurement
right
and then you could have high for both
and it always has to be described in
terms of the measurement that's being
taken because
the temporal
the temporal correlation
doesn't exist outside of the time series
that the correlation is being done on
and so
that is where benny introduces the model
based science it's like
like if you're talking at all about the
connectivity statistically defined
you're talking about a statistical model
on a specific experiment so even if
you're using a tool like a markov
blanket or a linear aggression that is
not posing in a priori scale
in that time series there isn't a priori
scale it's the specific time scale that
you measured
um
so yes
the edges can be of different kinds and
in neuroimaging again as we talked about
dot zero there's the anatomical the
functional and the effective
and so
wouldn't that be
simple if they were all the same but
it's just literally not the case there's
brain regions that don't have direct
connections to each other
that have temporal correlations and
there's ones that are directly connected
but they don't have temporal
correlations and every other
combination that's why we have to do
empirical measurement
so stephen
this
the the the difference as well is now we
see niche being brought in
when we have functional connectivity in
the brain
it's kind of assuming that it's all
brain
processes so you okay you've got the
brain and what's going on and the
connection between different areas now
if we start coming out and we start
looking at well there's active inference
with markov markovian approaches
okay there's brushing but brushing
is
an action
right reason is an action
coupled to a niche and the body and the
generative model
and so you've now come
and the niche it's not just that there's
a niche out there that's also
interacting
with
a kind of a brain based process you've
got a niche but there's also then
another recursion where okay we're now
looking at the idea
which is maybe been reformulated
conceptually more
of this whole thing happening
and this whole thing this whole process
this model
is in a niche itself
okay and there's i'm i'm creating in
this model
of this story
a functional connectivity which may be
substantiated through data if science is
used between brushing and reading
because the story has put that system of
information to me because i've never met
bob or alice and they most likely
fictional so there's an interesting move
from what started out as brain regions
being looked at
as functional connectivity
trying to then think what that's doing
because this
something out there this hidden states
to
an active influence agent where you now
have
action to give you a grounding to
jumping back out again to another sort
of
conceptual system of information which
we may be working with
to look at ourselves so
i think that that changes where does
that work niche fit
great thanks dean
i just think that if i'm
if i'm going to incorporate effect
effective
connectivity i'm actually looking at the
observer observing
so
if somebody
somebody throws me into a
cat scan machine starts taking slices on
my brain i'm sure they're going to be
able to point out some sort of a
functional connection between
what image pops out when i when it my
brain is focusing on the rabbit or my
brain is focusing on the duck
that functional connection will
definitely be able to show up in terms
of
some sort of differentiation
between those two
ways that i'm i'm perceiving that that
image
i think it's harder and maybe there's
because i don't know but maybe there is
some way of being able to show
how the brain is swapping
building the markov blanket
in situ
i don't know
but if there is a paper about that i'd
like to read it
because i know that i know the observer
in in
betty's
example here is swapping at some point
between
am i looking at bob
am i looking at alice or am i looking at
nine o'clock or am i looking at the swap
and i'm not sure if it's easy to be able
to show the swap part but it's
definitely there
great blue did you want to add it
something about the
the intransitivity of the volterra
ecological modeling
so i i had already mentioned it okay
yeah okay great steven
sort of it's gonna be a little bit of a
question but it's rhetorical if you want
it to be but
if we've got here
um
the relationship between
the the brain processing or the the body
processing
of the organism
there could be effective con
connectivity because there's some
common relational processes
if we're talking about
how they're
in their niche and maybe some
loose way that feedback loops can
reverberate through the buildings that
they're in and the social
miller
you can see the niche coming in
and then if we then go to well what in
this system of information
that we're engaging
so if alice and bob
are coupled
in our system information here
that could be functional
because we
i i i it's within
the variables that i assign to alice and
bob in whatever way that i'm embodying
this meaning making so i was wondering
if if those three
it sort of ties in a bit of what you've
got here but i i kind of feel it's
useful to
it starts to think about where was
fristen coming from when it was a kind
of a
trying to get at what the brain's doing
in response to
and really get at what's going on in
there
to when it's something which is actually
happening
to something again which becomes a kind
of an abstracted level and
i don't know which of those is closest
to what is normally being taught
or you know does that change between the
actual nature
of the the system do we do we have a way
to
to to think about that
or is that speaking to this um
process that when you just have dcm
models and you just have these kind of
informational models
that has to be kind of set
you have to kind of tell it and believe
that what you're talking about
the beauty of active inference is
i have
a deeper anchor to help me tether all of
those three
you know i have an embodied way of
knowing how it is to imagine i have an
embodied way of knowing how to brush and
read i have
um an embodied way
of enacting motor skills
um
in real time
to make the brushing and reading even
possible
and that's something that the previous
models
really got a plausible mechanism to
explain
until we got active influence
dcm doesn't seem to have that ability
it's all still kind of untethered
information based approaches
okay
interesting so i think
these
three
tale of three
cities now
we have
um
a
functional so these are predicated upon
observations of so
first to steven's point yes we could
think about brushing and reading as
affordances and embodiment and that is
something that active inference brings
to the table which is like the ability
to
zoom in
on one of these observations
and it's like well we're not just
studying the observation of brushing
there's an entity that's engaged in this
skillful action that's encultured and
that just takes you a million other
places so yes active inference is a
development on what fristen and others
have been doing for 30 years
we really have to be careful
whether we're using terms in their
technical
statistical sense or not like just to
show how easy it is to get mixed up you
can say well i mean brushing and reading
are correlated so it's like they're
effectively connected
but they're not that's called functional
connectivity functional connectivity is
the temporal correlation and then here's
how easy it is to get confused on the
other side
here's a story about the world where bob
does call alice but we are not
wiretapping
and bob says hey i'm brushing you should
read
and so
it turns out that in this world
not just are brushing and reading
functionally correlated
like they have a time series correlation
but actually brushing does
induce reading through a mechanism that
we didn't observe
that sounds like a functional
correlation
or a functional connection it's not
it's an effective connection
how it's technically defined the
influence of one system on another
and so yes function is happening action
is happening but it is very
important
that when thinking about these edges
people are accurate because these
stories are all happening at the same
time and different experimental designs
or statistical analyses
might not be contradictory to each other
they might be totally complementary to
each other
somebody might be describing
the enculturation of how brushing and
reading come to be
and somebody else might be talking about
the functional or the effect of
connectivity or all these other kinds of
pieces and so i agree active
helps us
understand the non-rival risk dynamics
of all these different descriptions
however we're going to be on the ground
floor forever
if we can't
be clear about what those different
descriptions are and adjust our regime
to these different
important
parts of the system
dave and then dean
okay dean and then dave if you unmute
later so dina then stephen and then yeah
so could you put a second thought bubble
uh under ec and could you be hey i'm
nine o'clocking are you
like because that to me is the effect of
connectivity i i keep the hey i'm
brushing you should read but also there
should be a second one hey i'm nine
o'clocking
are you nine o'clocking because that to
me is it speaks as much to the if effect
as opposed to the function
yes
good point and this there'd be depending
on how literal you want to take this
metaphor or how you're imagining the
story bob analysis or how close you want
to tie it to neural systems
one could imagine various pieces this is
just to highlight like that red is this
causal chain the difference that makes a
difference the actual phone call that
induces reading that's unobserved in
this experiment so fmri is measuring
blood oxygen level dynamics bold signal
and so that's not even neural activity
now read the spm textbook because that's
how you infer neuronal activity from the
bold signal but it's not what's being
directly measured
great
but but i just want to add so even the
observer is nine o'clocking
so now bob is nine o'clocking alice is
nine o'clock and the observer of bob and
alice is nine o'clock
that's the that's what i i kind of want
to bring into the conversation
yes totally agree like here's our um
happy scientists
don't know if there's a better icon to
represent the scientists but right
they're going to be observing
they're the ones who are making all of
these observations
and it's it's um
[Music]
it's somewhere between misguided to
dangerous
when it's like well this is simply how
it is it's like well no there's the
smiley guy
who's projecting that who's modeling
model-based science science is a social
practice
humans doing science
this is really important to keep in mind
um otherwise you might have you know a
smiley and a frowny and then they're
debating two different stories
and one is actually talking about the fc
and one is the ec and one's debating the
niche and you could have all these
different perspectives
and they don't have a common
rosetta stone
to actually come together
and some people are just talking about
what happens in principle no reference
to a data set someone else is talking
about an empirical correlation
coefficient from a specific data set
so yes
steven then blue
yeah this is very helpful to to map it
out like this and
it sort of gives a sense of this journey
of functional connectivity
functional um to
effective
and i'm
wondering whether
we the the process has evolved even
further to affective
connectivity um in the sense of like
alice could ring up bob and say hey bob
i i'm feeling good tonight
it's been a great day
okay
bob's like okay
i'm feeling good hey i'm gonna brush my
teeth
um
so
the the there's a there and uh i'm i'm a
bit more motivated to be into that big
book that i i really am not wasn't so
interested in before but i know alice
likes you know so there's a
is that is that kind of that extension
something that's almost could be charted
here from functional to effective to
affective
so
it's a good question we can imagine this
little variable because again we're not
um
in the territory we're on the map
if this variable
is bob's affect
and bob's affect has an edge
that is influencing how likely bob is to
undertake the policy selection of
calling alice
then yes
there is an effective edge
or a connectivity between the variable
corresponding to bob's affect
and then the policy
of what to say
and then
continue onwards but not every single
piece is
explored here but yes affects can enter
the picture and that's what's so fun and
exciting about these
incredibly composable and flexible
models like active inference so stephen
and then blue
and this also you know sort of harking
back to that earlier question about
social sciences and other sciences and
this actually does provide a useful
way to
have a construct to look even at arts
and the the sort of relationship people
be having so as you may be thinking
about
as people think about narratives and
stories as well as okay what is
explicitly happening and measurable
through modeling
what kinds of
relational
dynamics might be at play
and that itself could be a useful
boundary object in construction
co-creation
work because you started to get some
sort of framework again
provided you get some of the minimal
constructs clear so that it doesn't just
become noise
thanks blue
so i'm also wondering about the
relationship between functional
connectivity and effective connectivity
um and just really
i think about this always in in relation
to like gene expression right so you
know we
observe a functional connectivity
because
two genes are expressed in the same
tissue at the same time they're both
upregulated right so this is something
like that that daniel and i have studied
and maybe four into the rest of you guys
but um
effective connectivity also in terms of
gene expression is like there's a
downstream effector molecule right like
so there's a a molecule that has an
effect downstream of the gene expression
so like you know there's one
transcription factor that diffuses
through a tissue and then activates the
the transcription of something else
right
um and i wonder
so
it's not that i think functional
connectivity and effective connectivity
um can occupy the same space at the same
time but but what is it then when
there's
effective connectivity like i'm the
transfix i am the transcription factor
so i'm effectively connected to
downstream genes right
and so when i activate two genes at the
same time are those effectively
connected to the transcription factor
but functionally connected to each other
like i i wonder just if there's any
degree of overlap between functional
connectivity and effective connectivity
thanks dean
can i ask you a question blue
is is because i know nothing about genes
other than i wear them occasionally do
do
genes
automatically go
to the place of
affording us certain things as an effect
or can genes
be
an affordance as a cause because it
sounds to me knowing nothing about genes
that you're describing that you're
saying that genes can also be a cause
which i think would be really
interesting
but i'm not sure if that's i don't know
like
is it is gene only an effector or is
gene also an affordance around cause
so genes can be causes especially like
genes like transcription factors what i
was mentioning earlier um a
transcription factor just like activates
the transcription of other genes that's
like what it that's what its job is so
and and it's something that happens like
very normally during the processes of
development and the transcription
factors diffuse along axes and then it
you know causes like a cascade of um
you know developmental gene expression
timing that happens
so if it can be both a cause and effect
are you saying that it has
whether we whether we
measure it traditionally
with a time stamp that it it in effect
has a built-in affordance for time is
that because it's it sounds fascinating
if it's true because i said i don't know
anything about this but if that's the
case maybe some of the traditional ways
that we measure change
have to be reviewed
so
right like like in so i'm
let me see if i can understand your
question fully so in the process of
development there are specific genes
that are expressed in specific tissues
at specific times that aren't expressed
any other time so in that way it could
it could i i guess mark time is that
kind of what you're asking yeah
yes genes as kairos
is a very interesting idea like there
are certain critical periods where
developmental factors are expressed in
sequence but let me also respond to the
comment about what blue said about
genetics so
unsurprisingly genetics uses a different
ontology they use a different onft
actually ontology narrative formal
documents and tools than neuroscience
so when people in genetics
are describing functional
connectivity or functional interactions
call those connectivity
usually
for cellular biologists function is
equivalent to mechanism and so a
functional connection
would be like a mechanistic
physical linkage so two proteins that
bind that's called a protein-protein
interaction or like dna protein binding
like the transcription factor example
that blue mentioned so
that is often what is meant by
functional connectivity
effective connectivity i don't think is
used that much but if it were it would
be used informally to describe the
effect of one
on another
mechanistically
probably not in this time series
perturbation framework
and this is one of the most
fascinating areas like people talk about
gene networks or gene regulatory
networks
but there are multiple kinds of networks
that you can make
you can make networks of
proteins that bind to each other
you can make networks of proteins that
are
co-expressed so they have correlated
expression patterns which is functional
connectivity
but that doesn't mean that they're
functionally related there could be one
factor or a cellular scenario that
causes two genes to be upregulated so
they're going to appear in the same
coexpression group
and therefore a neuroscientist would say
that they're functionally connected
a
biologist might jump to say there's a
functional relationship or oh there's a
gene ontology enrichment of this
coexpression module so there's some sort
of functional relationship but it's
being used in a slightly different way
and
wouldn't that be fun to have shared
ontology for systems that ultimately are
related like gene expression and
neurophysiology
so blue and then stephen
okay let me just respond to that really
quickly okay so so take my gene
expression um
comment aside
let's go back to the brain so say there
are
two neurons that light up at the same
time they're not connected right so that
is a functional connection between those
two g neurons or brain regions right so
but let's just use neurons for the sake
of simplicity so two neurons that light
up at the same time they're they're
functionally connected
now one neuron that lights up and then
touches another neuron and tells it to
light up that's an effective connection
is that correct
yes or if you had a hidden third neuron
with a time delay and it influenced one
in one time step and it took two time
steps to get to the second one you would
see an effective connection between the
two that you measured because the second
one would always get activated after the
first one and so that's the challenge
with interpreting effective connectivity
as a mechanistic story
when actually a whole
diversity of mechanisms can give rise to
the observed empirical effect of
connectivity
okay but wait so here's my question like
i'm trying to see if there's any overlap
between this functional and effective
connectivity so say i have one neuron
that touches two neurons and tells those
two neurons to light up at exactly the
same time
is that
effective connectivity between the
original neuron and the two neurons that
light up subsequently and then
functional connectivity only between
those two neurons that light up at the
same time but are not touching is that
correct to think of it that way yes the
two children would have functional
connectivity because they have a
temporal correlation between remote
events however they would not have an
effective connectivity because activity
in one would be conditionally
independent upon activity in the other
and then from the point of view of that
parent's neuron
it would not have functional
connectivity
because let's just assume that it spikes
and then the next one and then the next
time step it's not spiking in the the
children are so it wouldn't have a
temporal correlation in its activity at
a lag of one it gets a little bit more
complex when we're talking about
time lag models
but it would have effective connectivity
through time
because it is like a directed edge
influencing them
and functional and effective are
independent of
the anatomical connectivity which is
what you'd find out with a microscope
without taking any measurements
so there's no overlap between these two
categories
there are situations where they can be
high for both or they can be low for
both
and the there can be anatomical
connectivity and functional or effective
or any combination it's like for two
nodes
there's like a tuple
of how strong that edge is
functionally effectively and
anatomically and it could be one one one
it could be negative one one negative
one it could be anything
so i'm trying to think of a circumstance
where something can be functionally and
effectively connected how is that
possible
so there would be um like
two
cryptocurrencies
who over the year time scale
have both gone up so at the course
graining they have a positive
correlation that's the functional
connectivity
and
they have a day-to-day correlation in
their movements
such that one moving leads the other um
that day
so then they'd have an effective
connectivity on the short time scale
because through time changes in one
caused the same direction of changes in
the other and when you zoom out they
have a broad scale correlation
got it so depending on the time scale
they can be functional or effective
yes and this is like where it does
matter exactly how there's not just one
way to do a time series correlation
because a time series correlation can be
just
um like
an arima model can have different time
horizons so one can look at the temporal
correlation like let's just say you had
two um out of phase oscillators
if you had a time horizon of one they
would have very strong negative
correlation
but if you had very very long time
windows they would have about the same
average
so you'd think that they were
uncorrelated for example so time series
correlations extremely depend on the
specifics of how it's calculated
which brings us back to model based
science
and you know a w for the
instrumentalists over the realists
and that's why benny is saying like yeah
don't get too concerned
about
whether we're finding cyclic or directed
acyclic models
because those are just modeling
conveniences that are downstream of the
experimental setup and the measurement
and the quantification techniques so
let's focus on that
and we'll see that we're engaged in
different flavors
of the scientific endeavor
and
ones that include humans and all the
ways that they work
and that just trying to look at that um
distilled kernel of like well the
coefficient is 0.7 so it's a module
that is
um a metaphysical conclusion
or an ontological conclusion being drawn
from a methodological process that might
be unwarranted
so in our oh yeah steven go for it yeah
i was so
if we were to take um
between these two and i think this has
really helped clarify because yeah i
think you're right the these words are
possibly open to
some confusion at first
if we're to take a brain scan in which
is essentially you've got the you know
you can have electrical
signals which aren't very easy to
identify
where they're coming from but you can
get a good sense of temporal fidelity
and then you've got fmri which tends to
be a bit more um over time
briston was bringing had has been
bringing that to the table the idea that
well what's the gen the more general
function at play and what's the type of
spatially
um
understood changes happening
over that temporal
depth
whereas
the effective connectivity might be more
like
what can we effectively say changes
between this and this
for a more specific
um definitive time scale would that be
one way that that you're talking about
the methods influencing which types of
models are relevant
um
that would tie into that
yes
awesome
point about um
sensor fusion
as well as the differences between fmri
and m and eeg
so eeg
is on the surface of the scalp although
you can also take electrical
measurements within the scalp
it's on the surface and it has extremely
fast temporal resolution like many many
times per second
and it's localized and it's measuring
electromagnetic activity
fmri
has a very different
spatial and temporal resolution
and it's measuring something different
which is the blood oxygenation dependent
signal inside of the brain which is
related to the hemodynamics and the
metabolic activity of brain regions and
the vasculature so they're measuring
different things
that's why it's so important that in
active style
models
that we clarify what our observations
are
and what the hidden states are that
we're doing inference on
and so one of the ways that sensor
fusion happens in
spm
is
so what's being described here is
multimodal integration of the eeg and
the fmri
is there's a latent unobserved variable
which is the neuronal activity and then
that neuronal activity at a given voxel
is going to have an edge
that outputs fmri measurements and then
another edge that measures eeg
outcomes
and then
what's happening with that unobserved
variable
is being fit
based upon
the
jointly measured fmri and eeg
so it's not just like you take a big
time series and do descriptive
statistics
but rather you use this hidden state
and that's what allows the generative
modeling
of brain activity
because you're fitting the hidden state
which gives rise to observations which
can be of totally different types
so
it is an awesome
thing to explore i hope we can continue
to delve into this type of like
sensor fusion and what these bayesian
graphical models actually enable dean
and then stephen
i'm trying to i'm trying to see if i can
come up with ways of being able to sort
of keep the effective connectivity and
functional connectivity segregated
before they're reintegrated
i don't know whether if we were to
we were to find ourselves out in the
middle of the wilderness and come upon
an ant hill and suddenly out of that ant
hill poured a bunch of elephants the
size of ants whether we would need to
look at the mechanics of that or we
would just be
drawn into the idea that now there's
these really
what
what was surprising and essentially
ant ant-sized elephants or if we saw
elephants suddenly walking or ambling
as though
they're still the normal-sized elephants
but petting
as though they were ants so taking the
tiniest of footsteps relative to their
overall scale i think that's where the
effective connectivity and the influence
based on something some of it based on
priors but essentially i want to keep
the functional and the effective apart
not that they can't overlap or that our
minds aren't able to
make those connections but i think each
serves a purpose
so that when we come up against
surprisal
we know
kind of what went into that
that moment or that event
i'm kind of seeing the size of the
animal as the the year performance of
the crypto and then the day-to-day
is the effective connectivity with the
footsteps so
yeah the scale piece all i was trying
the scale and relativity as opposed to
the sequence
interesting stephen and then there's a
question in live chat
i'm going to ask a little question
with this
again maybe rhetorical
over
the time scale of
this effective connectivity
um
it can effectively be brain bound to
some extent
um
when we have functional
connectivity
it's
the the
the
the measure
or the unit of analysis is implying
something outside
as being connected to that
or something that's a slightly more
macro i.e the idea of the function
that's being used
to
as a unit of analysis
then
um
give a way to get purchase on
temporal correlations would that
seem to be fair enough and would that
also possibly also then reflect the sort
of journey that's happened in cognitive
neuroscience
and computational neuroscience because
of
christian's work
it started to that that even in itself
brought in this
process of well what does it mean to
have function
[Music]
again we want to be
precise about what function means here
if the measurements are all brain
related
then that's the nodes
corresponding to the variables that
edges are going to be calculated within
if there are measurements that are
outside of the brain
then you can have functional or
effective connectivity amongst those
variables but we're not actually talking
about function like mechanistic impact
nor teleological impact in the niche
which is like the function of the hammer
is to nail things that's not what
functional is meaning here and just to
give an example of this is the um
awesome recent work by
guillaume dumas and collaborators
and so this is a toolkit that expands on
this
neuroimaging framework
and just says
well we're just going to concatenate
those matrices kind of reminds us of the
stochastic chaos paper 32 right like
when we went from having one coupled
system to having the two coupled systems
and then remember in the off diagonals
we had the effect of the two different
systems on each other
the causal impact of the systems on each
other
the effective connectivity of those
systems and so this is hyperscanning
where you have two
people
or it could be a human and a computer
whatever it is whatever the measurements
you're making are the rows and columns
on this matrix
and then you have that matrix the
measurements at each time slice going
through time it's a tensor and then you
do time series statistics on that tensor
and so these connections between the two
brains
are not anatomical
people's brains are not actually wired
up that way
however
you could calculate the functional
connectivity
which is not the function of one on the
other it's the temporal correlation
between the events and you could also
calculate the effective connectivity
which is what is the statistical impact
of one variable on another through time
whether or not that's the mechanistic
link
is a separate question
and that is what was revealed with this
example
was even if you hyper scan those
people's brains
and you see i mean come on
this brain region always leads this
other brain region in the other person
but that doesn't mean that's the
mechanistic connector it just means that
it's an effective connective edge
and so this
toolkit and this hyperscanning approach
like really demonstrate
that you can
have functional and effective
connectivity
amongst any variables that are being
measured in your experiment
but that's not the same thing as a
mechanistic story about what's happening
stephen
okay actually just one thing to clarify
so is that bottom diagram saying that
there's both
fmri and eec
there's there's electrical and um blood
flow measurements happening and they've
been integrated
um this one
uh so
in this paper
that was the sensor fusion that was the
integration of multiple neuro imaging
modalities fmri and eeg yeah yeah here
you could do sensor fusion hyper
scanning
or you could just have eeg on each
person or you could have eeg on one
person and fmri on the other you'd have
to qualify what it is that you were
actually measuring but this is a general
framework for
multi-agents
neuroimaging
statistics okay perfect so then the
point i was thinking that sort of
relates is
is you're i think it's this really
useful point that you say about how
it's not functional in some sort of
teleological sense however
sort of hidden in the in the linguistic
uh couching that's going on here for it
to be viable okay
not necessarily for it to be
experimentally how it's done is
implicitly
the effective connectivity
seems to be
couched on
or
there to be something meaningful
happening
or some some sort of process happening
effectively
a
one neuron has to exert something or
potentially have some
direct effect okay so there's
it's it's like a contingency
that's um
is present
functionally
it's like okay within
whatever functions going on but we don't
necessarily know what that is but within
some sort of process
there is something
happening that we can infer
is useful it's coming into play we're
not saying because we know they're
spatially
separated we can't say for sure then
um
or they're they're temporarily
hard too fuzzy
we can't necessarily say they have to be
connecting but functionally
we're getting a feel for
um
that this dynamic
is present rather than
this
almost more signal based approach
if there was more effective and i think
that that is
philosophically
couched in those two words
yes i totally hear you
um
the mathematical and the statistical
definitions are the ones that are being
calculated so
trying to read a lot into the english
word
and then apply that reading in to the
calculation is where we get a little
lost
because again the effect of connectivity
it doesn't mean that there's a
mechanistic relationship
you could have spatially remote neurons
that have an effective connectivity edge
like the example we discussed earlier
where there's a causal neuron and then
there's a it takes one time step to get
to this one and two to get the other
so then those two
recipient neurons are going to have an
effective connectivity edge
it's a hypothesis whether there's a
mechanistic edge but that's something
that you can explore
with science
is you can actually look at whether
then you test well what happens if i
silence this one you go wow the firing
pattern didn't change
so i falsified or reduced the posterior
likelihood of a mechanistic story that
involved a mechanistic edge it doesn't
invalidate the measurement of an
effective connectivity
it just means that you have to look
elsewhere for your mechanistic story you
know you shut down bob's phone
and there still is this effective
connection between the brushing the
teeth and the reading well now
you look back in the system iterated
scientific modeling
so i just want to ask this question from
the chat this will be our last
question and while final thoughts but
very fun and interesting and i hope next
week majid will join and that will be
great to hear his perspective as well so
joseph clark in the chat asked
how do you utilize functional and
effective connectivity in active
inference analysis to better inform an
answer to a question such as why i
scored the goal
i.e how does it enrich an analysis
so dean
yes something
i would need time to think about that
question so maybe that's
something i can think about and point to
because
right now
i'm trying to figure out if a gene is
both a cause and an effect
how is that then going to be
encapsulated and partitioned
because basically blue blew up my day
and now i'm going to need to go away and
rest for a little while and think about
this because if it's
if it's both
is there information just encapsulated
is that information partially
encapsulated because now it's a whole
bunch of genes that are
dealing with their betweenness
and all of that good stuff but again
again my final thought on this paper is
is that i think
whether we keep it on the
abstract level of something or partial
or whether we pull it down as he does in
the paper to the actual
moment of we're looking at something now
in particular
um
now i've got to sort of go and take that
off to the level of jeans and
see whether or not that
changes exactly it flipped my my duck
rabbit on a
i'm rolling downhill here i need to take
a break
um
i i agree i think this is an excellent
question because effective and
functional connectivity you'll find
like tens of thousands of citations in
the neurosciences
and you'll find people talking about the
applications and translational value of
neuroimaging
towards real life settings i'm sure
there's even neuroscience of
football or of soccer
so how do we actually connect all those
dots
and describe how
specifically within an active inference
framework
how do we think about these different
kinds of modularity
functional the effective the anatomical
the informational
how is that related to markov blankets
what's unique about the framing in
active inference compared to
the neural imaging that has existed for
40 years now much of it was also
developed by fristen but
still there's more to it so i think
these are great things so one thing that
we know we'll discuss is that question
how do we deploy
functional and effective connectivity so
that we can get better answers
we also want to talk about
modularity intransitivity and
preferences
and let's um
stephen and then any other last thoughts
what are you excited to discuss next
week
yeah i think this is a good question to
end and also start the next one um
i suppose one thing this idea of
that this is useful is how
ideas of how certain types of effective
connectivity
was important
for scoring a goal
like what
was tethered to what
in terms of the
connectivity and where are we talking
about something where
what's the dynamical system
the generative type of system
where that
involves making it happen
i get a sense that
the
functional approach
is more
connected to dynamical systems
thinking
and
in comparison to the effective approach
which might be more related to how
things are
potentially wired up and what's first
order second order third order
effects
so but
i don't know that other people see the
same but
it's helping me this is really useful
for me starting to think okay i see
where
briston was sort of coming in with this
question of how to address
um
these hidden states these hidden
dynamics
these hidden causes and how
by coming in it through this
functional
dynamical
inference approach
it
you could say it changes everything in
some ways so it certainly means that you
have to have more than one
um way to understand the hidden states
which is also like how the footballers
also got more than one way of trying to
understand what it even means to score
the appropriate sections being mixed
with visual being mixed with auditory
being mixed with
uh tactile
all these things are
some things do need to effectively
happen certain muscles need to happen in
a certain order if certain coordinated
action has to effectively happen for it
to even be possible but there might be
multiple dynamical functional ways that
i could
also bring
purchase and have different ways to get
to the same result
so
and again it's not
it becomes relevant
when you're trying to do the type of
measurements that are being designed for
a particular reason
so that you can get bet you're not going
to try and get at
the
short temporal
inferences through using fmri
and vice versa so i think that that's uh
something that's quite useful
great
my
closing thought will be
studying
the footballer is our football
as researchers of football
yeah
thanks dave
dean stephen blue
and
fun to participate today and thanks a
lot majeed for writing this
provocative paper and getting our 22
off on a good foot
in actin flap so thanks everybody for
listening please um get involved come
join us next week or a future week if
you'd like
and till next time